<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two treatises written by John Selden ... ; the first, Of the original of ecclesiastical jurisdiction of testaments ; the second, Of the disposition or administration of intestates goods.</title>
            <author>Selden, John, 1584-1654.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59102</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2442</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14343</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19084971</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19084971</idno>
            <idno type="VID">108531</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59102)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 108531)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 294:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two treatises written by John Selden ... ; the first, Of the original of ecclesiastical jurisdiction of testaments ; the second, Of the disposition or administration of intestates goods.</title>
                  <author>Selden, John, 1584-1654.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Basset ... and Richard Chiswell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXXIII [1683]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Probate law and practice --  England.</term>
               <term>Inheritance and succession --  England.</term>
               <term>Law --  England --  History and criticism.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:108531:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:108531:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TWO TREATISES Written by JOHN SELDEN OF THE INNER-TEMPLE, Eſquire. The Firſt, Of the ORIGINAL OF <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Iuriſdiction</hi> OF TESTAMENTS: The Second, Of the Diſpoſition or Adminiſtration OF Inteſtates Goods.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Baſſet</hi> at the <hi>George</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> and <hi>Richard Chiſwell</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. <abbr>MDCLXXXIII.</abbr>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:108531:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:108531:2"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <head>PART I. <hi>Of the Original of Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction of Teſtaments.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>CHAP. I. <hi>THE Intrinſecal Juriſdiction not given to the Church by the Civil Law,</hi> Page 1</item>
               <item>CHAP. II. <hi>Nor by the Canon Law.</hi> p. 3</item>
               <item>CHAP. III. <hi>The Extrinſecal Juriſdiction by the Civil Law, in whom,</hi> ibid.</item>
               <item>CHAP. IV. <hi>In whom by the Canon Law,</hi> p. 4</item>
               <item>CHAP. V. <hi>Of the Intrinſecal Juriſdiction in the</hi> Saxons <hi>time,</hi> p. 5</item>
               <item>CHAP. VI. <hi>Whence</hi> Linwood <hi>thinks the Juriſdiction Intrinſecal came to the Church,</hi> p. 9</item>
               <item>CHAP. VII. <hi>Teſtimonies of King</hi> John <hi>and</hi> Henry <hi>the Third's time, that may ſerve to prove the Extrinſecal Juriſdiction then in the Temporal Courts,</hi> p. 11</item>
               <item>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Suits of Legacies perſonal in the Spiritual Court from the beginning of</hi> Henry <hi>the Third, of the beginning of that Courſe,</hi> p. 12</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:108531:3"/>
               <head>PART II. <hi>Of the Diſpoſition of Adminiſtration of Inteſtates Goods.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>CHAP. I. <hi>In whom it was in the time of the</hi> Saxons, p. 15</item>
               <item>CHAP. II. <hi>In whom after the</hi> Normans <hi>until King</hi> John<hi>'s time,</hi> p. 17</item>
               <item>CHAP. III. <hi>In whom after the time of King</hi> John, p. 18</item>
               <item>CHAP. IV. <hi>How that ſo granted by King</hi> John<hi>'s Charter in Parliament hath continued of practice,</hi> p. 20</item>
               <item>CHAP. V. <hi>Of that of</hi> bona Inteſtatorum in manus Domini Regis capi ſolebant, p. 22</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:108531:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PART</hi> I. OF THE ORIGINAL OF Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction OF TESTAMENTS.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>The Intrinſecal Juriſdiction not given to the Church by the Civil Law.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Juriſdiction of Teſtaments being either <hi>Intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecal</hi> or <hi>Extrinſecal,</hi> (that is) either touching Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, or Recoveries of Legacies: Firſt for the <hi>Intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecal,</hi> it is clear that it came not to the Biſhop by Imitation; or otherwiſe, from the Imperial Civil Law: for by the elder part of that Law, regularly the Probate or Aperture of Wills was before the <note n="(a)" place="margin">ff. Teſt. quem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admodum aperiant. per tot. Et vide etiam Auth. 74. c. 2. ſit igitur Licentia.</note> 
                  <hi>Praetor.</hi> And afterward the obſignation, inſinuation and Probate of them in <hi>Rome,</hi> was before the <hi>Magiſter Cenſus,</hi> or <note n="(b)" place="margin">De Epiſc. l. 41. &amp; tit. de teſtam. l. 10. &amp; 23. &amp; Caput Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſ. ll. 4. tit. 4. l. 4. Ubi viſendus inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pres vetus:</note> 
                  <hi>apud officium Cenſuale,</hi> as it were before the Barons of our Exchequer; and that continued into later time. And the ſame Officer by the name of <note n="(c)" place="margin">Authent. 44. &amp; ibid. Cujacius, &amp; vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſis Gloſſ. Graeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barb. Meurſii in <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <hi>generalis</hi> in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> had the ſame authority: But alſo afterwards as well the <hi>Queſtor</hi>'s Seal, as that of the <hi>generalis</hi> became to be uſed at the obſignation, and his authority alſo in the Probate or Aperture.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:108531:4"/>And the Emperour <hi>Leo</hi> 
                  <note n="(d)" place="margin">Novel 44. for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulas ver. Teſtam. aperiendorum, vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis I. Paul Regeſt. ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. l. 4. tit. 6. &amp; Marculph. Formul. l. 2. c. 37. &amp; 38.</note> about the year 890. transferred all that herein belonged to the <hi>Generalis</hi> into the <hi>Queſtor</hi>'s place; yet ſo, that ſome other Civil Magiſtrates had the like authority: and what was done before theſe in <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> was in other Cities be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their Chief Governours, as <hi>Defenſores</hi> or <hi>Praeſides:</hi> neither was the Church permitted to have to do with the Inſinuation of Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaments, but expreſly forbidden by a reſcript
<note n="(e)" place="margin">C. de Epiſc. &amp; eler. l. 41. repetita.</note> of the Emperour <hi>Juſtin:</hi> nor is any thing that gives it either among the <hi>Novells</hi> of the <hi>Greek</hi> Empire, or in the <hi>Lombarda,</hi> or <hi>Capitulares,</hi> which have
<note n="(f)" place="margin">Hoſtienſ. in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oem. ſum. &amp; vetuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ores canoniſt. paſſim.</note> been reputed as parts alſo of the Imperial Law.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:108531:4"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Nor by the Canon Law.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NEither in any General Council, or other part of the received Canon Law, doth any Teſtimony occurr, that gives the Church this <hi>Intrinſecal Juriſdiction.</hi> But in the fourth Council of <note n="(a)" place="margin">Cap. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage</hi> holden in the year 398. it was ordained, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Epiſcopus tuitionem teſtamentorum non ſuſcipiat.</hi> And this being then eſtabliſhed by two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and fourteen Biſhops, was afterwards made a part of
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Diſt. de ſecular. negotiis, cap. 5.</note> the Decrees, or <hi>Canon</hi> Law, collected by <hi>Gratian,</hi> and publiſhed and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized by Pope <hi>Eugenius</hi> the Third about 1150. and the Gloſs upon that Canon interprets <hi>tuitio</hi> for <hi>Aperture</hi> or <hi>Probate.</hi> So alſo Pope <note n="(c)" place="margin">Ad c. nos qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem extra tit. de teſtament.</note> 
                  <hi>Innocent</hi> the Fourth underſtands it: <hi>publicatio</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>fieri non debet apud Epiſcopum;</hi> and he vouches that Law, <note n="(d)" place="margin">Tit. de Inſtrum. edit. S. oſtenſ. 34. vid. D. D. ad c. nos quidem, &amp;c. ſi haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des extra tit. de teſt. &amp; Linwood de teſt. c. item S. infin. &amp; cap. ſtat. S. approb.</note> 
                  <hi>Conſulta ducalia tit. de Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament.</hi> to prove it. <hi>Speculator, Hoſtienſis</hi> and others of the ſame time, and generally the reſt that follow them, make the <hi>Civil Law</hi> only the ſquare of the Juriſdiction of the <hi>Probates;</hi> and ſo it is truly affirmed in our Books, that the <hi>Probate</hi> belongs not to the Church <note n="(e)" place="margin">2 R. 3. Teſt. 4. 14 H. 7. ſo. 12. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> by the Spiritual Law; neither is any ſuch thing given by any later
<note n="(f)" place="margin">Quod diſcimus ex Bullarii ſumma quam edidit S. Gua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranta.</note> Bull, or Decretal from the Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>The Extrinſecal Juriſdiction by the Civil Law, in whom.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOr the <hi>Extrinſecal</hi> Juriſdiction that gave <hi>Recoveries of Legacies,</hi> by the Imperial Civil Law, where the Legacies were <hi>in pios uſus,</hi> the <note n="(a)" place="margin">C. de Epiſc. &amp; Cler. l. 28. Nulli, &amp; l. 49. ſi quis ad de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinand authentic. 135. c. 10. &amp; vid. c. 11.</note> Biſhop of the Dioceſs ſometimes by himſelf, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times with the Civil Magiſtrate, provided for the execution of the Teſtators meaning: otherwiſe the Juriſdiction of Legacies, and what elſe falls under Teſtamentary diſpoſition, was and <note n="(b)" place="margin">ff. de Petit. hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. &amp; tit. de legat.</note> is the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates only.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:108531:5"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>In whom by the Canon Law.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BUt by the <hi>Canon Law,</hi> the general care of execution of Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments is committed to the Biſhop: yet I find not any <hi>Canon</hi> to that purpoſe received into the Body of that Law, now in authority, before the time of the <hi>Decretals;</hi> which have out of ſome Council of <hi>Mentz</hi> theſe words, <hi>viz. <note n="(a)" place="margin">Extr. de teſt. c. 6.</note> Si haeredes juſſa Teſtatoris non impleverint, ab Epiſcopo loci illius omnis Res quae eis relicta eſt Canonice interdicatur, cum fructibus &amp; caeteris emolumentis, ut vota defuncti impleantur.</hi> Out of what Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Mentz</hi> this is taken, I have not yet learned;
<note n="(b)" place="margin">Lib. 15. c. 34.</note> but in the ſame ſyllables it occurrs in <hi>Burchard,</hi> that lived about ſix hundred years ſince, with the Marginal Note of <hi>ex Concilio Moguntino.</hi> What other Texts are, touching the power of the Canons over performance of Teſtaments, have reference to that courſe ordained by the Civil Law, where any thing was given <hi>in pios uſus,</hi> not to a general Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction; for ſo is the Canon <hi>Nos quidem extr. tit. de teſtam.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is that Canon <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltima Voluntas</hi> in <hi>C.</hi> 13. <hi>q.</hi> 2. taken out of S. <hi>Gregory,</hi> otherwiſe to be underſtood, if you interpret it as you ought by thoſe <note n="(c)" place="margin">Videſis Greg. lib. 3. Epiſt. 9. &amp; lib. 9. Epiſt. 20.</note> places of <hi>Gregory</hi> whence it is taken: but the Canoniſts generally upon that Canon <hi>Si haeredes,</hi> take it, that <hi>executio teſtamentorum ad Epiſcopos ſpectat.</hi> And ſo thoſe old ones Pope <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> the Fourth, <hi>Bernard,</hi> and others of the reſt deliver; and the <note n="(d)" place="margin">Vid. Gonzal. Zuarez Prax. Eccleſ. Lam. 2. Praelud. 2. Sect. 44. &amp; Zerula prop Epiſcop. verb. leg. ad quaeſt. 9.</note> latter follow them, yet they commonly reſtrain it (and that in practice in other States) to Legacies given <hi>in pios uſus.</hi> And in the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> where twice the Biſhops power over Teſtaments is provided for, <note n="(e)" place="margin">Seſſ. 12. de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form. cap. 6. &amp; Seſſ. ult. de reformat. c. 4.</note> nothing is ſpoken of but Commutations of Lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and of ſuch as are given <hi>in pios uſus:</hi> yet from Ancient time both the <hi>Intrinſecal</hi> and <hi>Extrinſecal</hi> Juriſdiction of Teſtaments made of perſonal Chattels in <hi>England,</hi> hath been and is in the Church, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in places where ſpecial Cuſtom excludes it: the original whereof being not ſufficiently found in either of theſe Laws (the Civil and Canon) divers parts of which according to the various admiſſion of ſeveral Eſtates have been much diſperſed through <hi>Chriſtendome,</hi> and ſome remain now exerciſed by <hi>imitation</hi> among us; It reſts, that diſquiſition be made for it in the Monuments of the Kingdom, that according as they together with the Canons afford light, ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture may be had touching the Antiquity and ground of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:108531:5"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Of the Intrinſecal Juriſdiction in the</hi> Saxons <hi>time.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Eldeſt Teſtament that I have ſeen made in <hi>England,</hi> is that of King <hi>Edgar</hi>'s time, made by <note n="(a)" place="margin">Iamb. Peramb. Cant. p. 548.</note> one <hi>Birthric</hi> a <hi>Gentleman</hi> or <hi>Thane</hi> (it ſeems) of great worth, and his Wife <hi>Elſwith;</hi> wherein they deviſe both Lands and Goods; and in the end of the Will ſayes her husband. <hi>
                     <hi>And ic hidde for goder lufan minne leofan Hlaford. ꝧ He ne þafige ꝧ ae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ig man uncerne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>pide aƿende;</hi> And I pray for Gods love my leefe Lord, that he doe not ſuffer that any man our Teſtament do break.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It may perhaps thence be collected, that the Protection or Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Teſtament was within the Juriſdiction of the Lords Court, as alſo the Probate; and that eſpecially, becauſe divers <hi>Lords <note n="(b)" place="margin">Henſloes Caſe 9. Rep. <hi>b.</hi>
                     </note> of Mannors</hi> have to this day the Probate of Teſtaments by Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom continued, againſt that which is otherwiſe regularly ſetled in the Church. But the ſame Teſtament being for Lands as well as for Goods, it may be that this Clauſe had reference to the Lord in regard of the Land only, (to the Alienation of which, his Aſſent might be requiſite) or to denote him for the Teſtators beſt friend, as one choſen Overſeer of his Will; and indeed he deſires all other good people to ſee his Will be not broken; which makes me only offer it, as what another mans fancy may work on: but I conceive not out of it enough to prove either way any thing touching the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction of Teſtaments.</p>
               <p>Nor in the <hi>Saxon</hi> times appears any thing that can ſufficiently direct us to know, how it was exerciſed here, unleſs out of that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Siwerth</hi> of <hi>Durham</hi>'s Teſtament, in the <note n="(c)" place="margin">In Bibli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>thec. Cottoniana.</note> Book of <hi>Ely,</hi> you may collect, that the Probate was ſupply'd in the life-time of the Teſtator by Inrolment, or leaving an Indented Copy of it with the <hi>Alderman</hi> or <hi>Sheriff</hi> of the County, in whoſe <hi>County-Court</hi> the moſt of proceedings of Temporal Juſtice, and of the Spiritual alſo (for the Biſhop ſate with him, as in his Conſiſtory) were in the <hi>Saxon</hi> times: for ſo much perhaps may be conjectured out of it, as we faithfully here relate it. <hi>Siwerth</hi> in King <hi>Edgar</hi>'s time, lying ſick at <hi>Lindane</hi> in the <hi>Iſle of Elie,</hi> makes his Teſtament, and ſends for <hi>Brithnorth</hi> Abbot of <hi>Elie,</hi> and divers of the Monks, and others of the Gentry; and the Abbot writes the Teſtament <hi>in tribus Chirographis, coram</hi> (ſo are the words of the Book) <hi>cunctis fecit recitari, lectum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fecit incidi, unamque partem Chirographi retinuit Siferthus, Alteram au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem dedit Abbati, tertiam vero miſit ſtatim per praefatum Brithelmum</hi> (that was one of the Gentlemen of the Countrey then preſent) <hi>Ailwino Aldermano, qui tunc temporis degebat in Elie, &amp; petiit ab illo ut ſuum Teſtamentum ſtare concederet, quomodo Abbas allud ſcripſenat, <note place="margin">In lib. conceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſiet.</note> &amp; ordinaverat apud Lindane corum praedictorum Teſtimonio virorum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cum itaque Ailwinus Alderman hoc audiſſet, &amp; Chirographum vidiſſet, re miſit illico ad eum Wlnothum de Stowe cum Brithelmo, ſciſcitatuſque eſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:108531:6"/>ab eo quid aut quomodo vellet de Teſtamento ſuo: qui mox per coſdem renuntiavit ei, ſic ſuum Teſtamentum abſque omni contradictione vel mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatione ſe velle ſtare, ſicut praefatus Abbas illud in Chirographo poſuerat, quod ut Ailwinus Alderman audivit, totum conceſſit, ut ſtaret ſient ipſe Siverthus Teſtatus erat.</hi> But in deed, in it Lands lying in <hi>Durham</hi> were deviſed to the Abbey; and ſo, it was not only of perſonal Chattels.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Saxon</hi> Laws are very ſilent of any thing touching Teſtaments; and we muſt remember, while we think of that example of <hi>Suverth</hi> of <hi>Durham,</hi> that the Eccleſiaſtical and Temporal Courts of Common Juſtice, held as one by the Sheriff and Biſhop, were not ſevered as now, into the Conſiſtory, and County Court, until the <hi>Conqueror</hi> did it by a Law yet remaining and elſewhere publiſhed
<note n="(d)" place="margin">V. Spicilegia in Eadmerum.</note>.</p>
               <p>In what intercedes from this time, until about <hi>H.</hi> 2. I find not any Teſtimony that gives light to this purpoſe; as the <hi>Saxon</hi> Laws, ſo thoſe of the <hi>Conquerour,</hi> and of <hi>H.</hi> 1. and <hi>H.</hi> 2. mention nothing that taſts of either kind of Juriſdiction of Teſtaments; only of a Charter of <hi>H.</hi> 1. extant in <hi>Matth. Paris,</hi> and in the <hi>Red Book</hi> of the Exchequer this occurrs, <hi>Si quis Baronum vel hominum meorum infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mabitur, ſicut ipſe dabit vel dare juſſerit pecuniam ſuam, ita datam eſſe concedo.</hi> This may perhaps ſeem to denote, that the Kings Court de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined of Legacies, eſpecially of the Kings Tenants.</p>
               <p>But indeed it proves not ſo much. But the eldeſt paſſage that proves clear enough here, is that which makes the <hi>Intrinſecal</hi> Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction t ohave been in the Church, and the <hi>Extrinſecal</hi> in the Kings Court; I mean that which is found in the Treatiſe attributed to <hi>Randall</hi> of <note n="(e)" place="margin">Lib. 7. cap. 6. &amp; 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Glanvill</hi> Chief Juſtice under <hi>H.</hi> 2. where he ſayes, that <hi>if a Legacy be detained, the Executors or other friends of the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtator, were to get the Kings</hi> Writ <hi>to the Sheriff, commanding quod juſtè &amp; ſine dilatione facias ſtare rationabilem diviſum,</hi> (that is, the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt or Legacy) <hi>N. ſicut rationabiliter monſtrari poterit quod eam fecerit, &amp; quod ipſam ſtare debeat, &amp;c.</hi> And it is plain by the words there preceding and ſubſequent, that it hath reference to moveable or perſonal poſſeſſions, not to Lands, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So that it ſeems clear by that in <hi>H.</hi> 2. his time, the Juriſdiction of perſonal Legacies was in <hi>Secular Courts.</hi> But if the Iſſue in Secular Courts upon that Writ came to be, whether the Teſtament were true or no, or well made, or whether the thing demanded were <hi>in facto</hi> bequeathed, <hi>Tum</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>placitum illud in Curia Chriſtianitatis audiri debet, &amp; ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minari, quià placitum de Teſtamentis coram Judice Eccleſiaſtico fieri debet, &amp; per illorum qui Teſtamento interſuerint teſtimonia ſecundum ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris ordinem terminari:</hi> that is, as it muſt be underſtood, that upon iſſue of bequeathed or not bequeathed, of Teſtament made, or no Teſtament, the <hi>Tryal</hi> muſt have been otherwiſe than by the practice of the latter
<note n="(f)" place="margin">29 Ed. 3.33. <hi>a.</hi> 44 Ed. 3.16. <hi>a.</hi> Perk. 493. 22H. 6.52.</note> Law, wherein the Teſtament is traverſable, and the Traverſe tryable in the Kings Court by <hi>Certificate</hi> to the Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Court from the Eccleſiaſtical, as at this day, of <hi>Inſtitution, Baſtardy,</hi> and <hi>Profeſſion</hi> in Religion, and the like: and thence may it be well concluded, that at this time by the practiſed Law, the Probate or the Intrinſecal Juriſdiction was in the Church; for as the <hi>Inſtitution,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:108531:6"/>Baſtardy</hi> and <hi>Profeſſion</hi> are to be certified, becauſe within the Biſhops Juriſdiction. Some recorded Teſtimonies remain of the firſt and third, and the nature of the Marriage or Cohabitation (that directs in the ſecond) is to be judged of only in the Spiritual Courts; ſo the <hi>Validity of the Teſtament,</hi> or the truth of this or that particular Legacy was to be certified from the Spiritual Court, becauſe the Probate had there proceeded, and the Copy there remaining was moſt authentick; otherwiſe to what purpoſe ſhould they have ſent to the Spiritual Court in ſuch a caſe?</p>
               <p>But on the other ſide, as in the caſe of <hi>Inſtitution, Profeſſion</hi> and <hi>Baſtardy,</hi> the conſequence of them, which are objects of their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſecal Juriſdiction, as <hi>Deſcent, Excluſion</hi> from Inheritance, gaining it by a deſcent caſt, or legal making a Church full, or the like are determinable only at the Common Law; ſo the conſequence of a Teſtament, that is, the Recoveries of Legacies, and ſuch like, as it ſeems by that Writ, were in the Temporal, not in the Spiritual Court. I know the authority of that Treatiſe is ſuſpected, and ſome of the beſt and ancienteſt Copies having the name of <hi>E. de N.</hi> which I have heard from diligent ſearchers in this kind of Learning, affirmed to have been ſometimes <hi>E. de Narborough,</hi> and not <hi>R. de Glanvilla,</hi> it hath been thought to be anothers Work, and alſo of later time. But, as on the one ſide, I dare not be confident, that it is <hi>Glanvills,</hi> ſo I make little queſtion, that it is as ancient as his time, if not his Work. The Teſts of the Precedents of Writs under his name, the language, eſpecially the name of <hi>Juſtitia</hi> alwayes for that which we now from ancient time call <hi>Juſtitiarius;</hi> and <hi>Juſtitia</hi> was ſo uſed in
<note n="(g)" place="margin">Ita Jo. Salisbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genſis de Nugis Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial. lib. 5. cap. 15. &amp; 16.</note> Writers under <hi>H.</hi> 2. and the Law delivered in it taſteth not of any later Age. And howſoever it comes to paſs, the <hi>Regiam Majeſtatem</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by Command of <hi>David</hi> the Firſt under the time of our <hi>Hen.</hi> 1. hath for the moſt part the ſame ſyllables with this ſuppoſed <hi>Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill,</hi> and expreſly <note n="(h)" place="margin">Regiam Majeſtat. lib. 3. cap. 38.</note> the very paſſages and the Writ that we have now here noted for Teſtaments.</p>
               <p>That Extrinſecal Juriſdiction of thoſe times in the Secular Courts, was perhaps denoted by thoſe words in the Teſtament of <hi>Theobald</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> under King <hi>Stephen, <note n="(i)" place="margin">Jo. Sarisburg. Epiſt. 57.</note> Supremis</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>deficientium voluntatibus ſuum accommodant jura favorem,</hi> where he deviſes only perſonal things and uſes. I think, <hi>Jura</hi> is rather to be taken for the Common Law, than the Spiritual; which is, in the moſt uſual phraſe of that time, deſigned by <hi>Canones.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this time of <hi>Hen.</hi> 2. divers fierce Controverſies fell between the Law and Spiritual Juriſdiction, and the particulars of them are largely related at the end of <hi>Quadrilogus,</hi> in <hi>Gervaſe</hi> of <hi>Dover,</hi> in <hi>Roger</hi> of <hi>Wendover,</hi> in <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> and <hi>Matthew Paris,</hi> but in him moſt abruptly; yet not the leaſt mention is in them touching any matter of this Juriſdiction; and in the main Caſes of our Spiritual Courts depending under <hi>H.</hi> 2. and ſent by appeal to <hi>Rome,</hi> which yet remain in the Epiſtles of <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> there is not one that touches up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on either of theſe Juriſdictions of Teſtaments in the Church; but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed there is one that may ſeem ſomewhat to prove for that which
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:108531:7"/>we note out of <hi>Glanvill,</hi> concerning the Intrinſecal Juriſdiction at that time in the Temporal Court: for in an Appeal ſent to Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the Third, the Caſe, as <hi>John</hi> 
                  <note n="(k)" place="margin">Epiſt. 89.</note> of <hi>Salisbury</hi> relates it, was, that one <hi>Richard de Aneſtia in foro ſecularium Judicum petitionem haereditatis ad bona avunculi obtinenda inſtituit,</hi> againſt <hi>Mabile de Franck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villa,</hi> being Daughter to <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Sackvill,</hi> to whom the Plaintiff was Nephew by his Siſter: and the point of the iſſue between the Daughter here and the Nephew, being upon the Baſtardy of the Daughter, the Spiritual Court had the Tryal of it. If <hi>(bona)</hi> here be underſtood for Chattells, as in our Law it is, and ſo reſtrained, then was this <hi>petitio haereditatis,</hi> as a Suit for <hi>Sackvill</hi>'s Goods, grounded alſo, as it ſeems, upon a Teſtament of his: for in the rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Caſe alſo, <hi>Richardus inſiſtebat,</hi> ſayes the Author, <hi>inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioni Avunculi, petitionem haereditatis inſtituens;</hi> and on the other ſide, <hi>Mabile maxime Patris noviſſmae voluntati innitebatur:</hi> which ſhews, that here was a Teſtament in the Caſe, and a Suit for what was challenged by it in the Temporal Court: But <hi>haereditas</hi> and <hi>bona,</hi> it is likely, included here (as by the Civil Law) all poſſeſſions of the Anceſtor, both real of Inheritance, and perſonal, that is, the <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſum jus defuncti,</hi> and not only our inheritance; although it doth alſo amongſt ſome <note n="(l)" place="margin">Barth. ad tit. de ſumma Tr. l. 1. num. 42.</note> Civilians denote no more, if at leaſt they underſtand aright what they ſay, while they write, that <hi>conſuetudo eſt in Anglia quâ primogenitus ſuccedit in omnibus bonis:</hi> and in this Caſe, if the Iſſue had been upon the Truth of the Teſtament, as it was upon the Baſtardy, it had been referred alſo to the Spiritual Judges.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:108531:7"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Whence</hi> Linwood <hi>thinks the Juriſdiction Intrinſecal came to the Church.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BY what is before delivered, it appears, that the <hi>Intrinſecal Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction</hi> or <hi>Probate</hi> was in the Church; and that by expreſs te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, as anciently as the time of <hi>H.</hi> 2. and by all probability it was in ſetled uſe before that time, being ſpoken of in that Treatiſe called <hi>Glanvill</hi>'s, as a known courſe of proceeding: although indeed yet I could never ſee an expreſs Probate in any particular caſe, elder than about <hi>H.</hi> 3. But the beginning or courſe of this <hi>Intrinſecal</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction in the Church, is not for ought I have yet learned, extant: however <hi>Fairefaxe</hi> tells us, that it was by an Act of Parliament, <note place="margin">2 R. 3. tit. Teſlam. 4.</note> which perhaps he took from that of <hi>Linwood; <note place="margin">Tit. de Teſt. C. ſtat. verb. Eccleſia libert.</note> Haec libertas (Eccleſiae) quoad approbationem hujuſmodi</hi> (ſaith <hi>Linwood</hi>) <hi>fundatur ſuper conſenſu Regio, &amp; ſuorum Procerum (in talibus) ab antiquo, conceſſo.</hi> Where he means by <hi>in talibus,</hi> their power of committing of Adminiſtration of Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates goods, as it is plain by his quotation of that Conſtitution of Arch-Biſhop <hi>Stafford tit. de immunitate Eccleſ. accidit. novitate perverſas guidam etiam:</hi> That power was given, as I gueſs, by Parliament in King <hi>John</hi>'s time: but thereof more in due place. And <hi>Linwood</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, <hi>Item fundatur ſuper conſuetudine in ea parte de ſcientia Regum Angliae, diutius conſervata:</hi> Which is indeed, that it is founded upon the Common Law or Cuſtomary Law of the Kingdom; or that it hath like antiquity or original as other parts of the Common Law, that is, immemorial Cuſtom. For though it be exerciſed according to the Civil and Canon Law in the Spiritual Courts, with ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference had to the Cuſtoms of <hi>England;</hi> yet it is clear, that the power which the Spiritual Courts have to exerciſe it, is meerly by the Common Law; although we find not when it came firſt to them, no more than we find divers of our ſetled Courſes and Maxims in the Common Law; touching which yet we can without much difficulty prove, that at ſuch or ſuch times they were not in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice; as perhaps in the more ancient Ages, this was not in theſe Courts. But that it was originally belonging to the Crown, that is, to the <hi>Temporal Courts,</hi> which are all, and ever were derived from the Dignity Royal, is affirmed alſo, as in that cited in <hi>Henſloe</hi>'s Caſe, out of <hi>Jocelin</hi>'s Hiſtory of the Arch biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> in a Writ <note n="(a)" place="margin">Cod. MS. Hoſp. S. Leonardi in Bib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lioth. Cottoniana.</note> 2 <hi>H.</hi> 5. that prohibiteth the Arch-biſhop of <hi>York</hi> to call the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutors of the Tenants of S. <hi>Leonard</hi>'s Hoſpital to prove their Wills before him; becauſe as the words are, <hi>placita de cognitionibus ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptorum in Regno noſtro Angl. ad Nos, Coronam &amp; dignitatem noſtram ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialiter pertinent:</hi> and alſo they had time out of mind uſed to prove them before the Maſters and Brothers of the Hoſpital. Here we ſee the <hi>Teſtaments</hi> reckoned as other <hi>Evidences,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Henſloes Caſe apud v. cl. Ed Cook par. 9. fo. 37, 38, 48.</note> the Tryal and Conuſance whereof belongs only to the Temporal Courts: and at this day
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:108531:8"/>by ſpecial Cuſtom many Lords of Mannors have like <hi>Probate</hi> in their <hi>Courts Baron.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By the way, <note place="margin">That in <hi>France</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates are in the Spiritual Courts.</note> for that which <hi>Fairefaxe,</hi> and others following him, tells us, that in all other Countries the <hi>Probate</hi> belongs to Lay-Judges, he is deceived, and deceives his Readers. Indeed, in the moſt places of other States it belongs to the Lay-Judges: but in <hi>France</hi> 
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">Choppin. de Dom. Franciae lib. 2. pag. 230. Edit. 1588. &amp; videſis teſtam. Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olodi Abbatis Flori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ani Helgundi initio.</note> generally the Spiritual Judges, both before <hi>Fairefaxe</hi> his time and ſince, had this Juriſdiction of <hi>Probate,</hi> and ſo have had with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out controverſie ever ſince the diſputations about it and other parts of Juriſdiction had with ſome Clergy-men, by <hi>Coniers</hi> Attorney Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral to <hi>Philip Valois,</hi> and <hi>Peter Dreux</hi> in behalf of the Duke of <hi>Britain,</hi> at ſuch time as the Clergy had there ſo extended their Juriſdiction, <hi>Que les Fauxbourgs eſtoint trois fois plus grands que la uille,</hi> as <hi>Paſquire</hi> ſpeaks of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:108531:8"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Teſtimonies of King</hi> John <hi>and</hi> Henry <hi>the Third's time, that may ſerve to prove the Extrinſecal Juriſdiction then in the Temporal Courts.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOr the <hi>Extrinſecal</hi> Juriſdiction, as it ſeems by <hi>Glanvill</hi> and other Teſtimonies, that it was in the Kings Courts under <hi>H.</hi> 2. and ſo by all probability before: ſo out of other Records of following time, ſomewhat may perhaps be collected to prove, that it continued long in them, as out of the <hi>Patent</hi> of King <hi>John</hi> for <hi>Oliver</hi> of <hi>Roch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi>'s Teſtament, <hi>Sciatis</hi> (ſayes
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Patent. 3. Reg. Johan. membr. 6.</note> the King) <hi>Nos conceſſiſſe Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum Oliveri de Rupe forti ſicut rationabiliter conditum eſt, &amp; apud S. Florentiam veterem &amp; Rupem fortem ſcriptum &amp; ordinatum. Quare volumus &amp; firmiter praecipimus quod nullus Executorum Teſtamenti ipſius impediat quin illud ſicut rationabiliter conditum eſt faciant.</hi> Then out of that of <hi>Peter de Roches</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> and Chief Juſtice of <hi>England,</hi> touching the Will of <hi>Adam</hi> of <hi>Gurdun, Rex <note n="(b)" place="margin">Rot. Clauſ. Joh. Membr. 22.</note> Dom. P. Winton. Epiſc. Juſtic. Angl. &amp;c. Mandamus Vobis quod teneri facias Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtamentum Adae de Gurdun quod fecit de Rebus ſuis mobilibus &amp; omnibus aliis in Angl. ſecundum diſpoſitionem teſtamenti excepta terra quam de domino noſtro habuit ſeptimo Auguſti. Teſte meipſo:</hi> this expreſly gives ſome legal execution of a Teſtament made of perſonal things unto the <hi>Chief Juſtice</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> And in
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Clauſ. 5 H. 3. part. 2. m. 7. &amp; 15.</note> 5 <hi>H.</hi> 3. <hi>Robert</hi> of <hi>Lexin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> having the poſſeſſion of all the goods of <hi>Philip de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>letott</hi> the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtator, a <hi>Writ</hi> goes out to him to pay <hi>William</hi> Earl of <hi>Salisbury</hi> a debt of Ninety Marks out of them, and that the reſt ſhould be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to the Executors <hi>ad faciendum Teſtamentum;</hi> and another <hi>Writ</hi> was ſent, that he ſhould <hi>per viſum &amp; Teſtimonium Execut.</hi> ſell all <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>letott</hi>'s goods, <hi>&amp; denarios quos inde fieri feceritis, ſalvo faciatis reponi ſub ſigillo veſtro &amp; ſigillo Executor. pradict. donec aliud mandatum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum inde habueritis.</hi> And in 7 <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. a <hi>Writ</hi> is directed to the Sheriff of <hi>Lincoln,</hi>
                  <note n="(d)" place="margin">Clauſ. 7 H. 3. part. 1. membran. 16. idem id ipſum eſt quod habetur in commentario 9. v. c. Ed. Cooke, f. 38.6. ſumptum eſt.</note> reciting, that whereas it appeared, that <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Fitz-dune</hi> dyed not Inteſtate, <hi>Ideo tibi praecipimus quod omnia Catalla ipſius Richardi in Manum noſtram capta in balliva tua ſine di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latione habere facias Priori de Noketon,</hi> and other Executors of his Teſtament <hi>ad faciendum inde rationabile teſtamentum:</hi> and other like <hi>Writs</hi> occurr in the Rolls of King <hi>John</hi> and <hi>H.</hi> 3.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:108531:9"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Suits of Legacies perſonal in the Spiritual Court from the beginning of</hi> Henry <hi>the Third, of the beginning of that Courſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BUt however it may ſeem by thoſe Teſtimonies, that the Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Courts had ſome <hi>Extrinſecal</hi> Juriſdiction of Teſtaments in the time of King <hi>John</hi> and <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. it is clear, that in the beginning of <hi>H.</hi> 3. <hi>Suits for Legacies</hi> perſonal were in the Spiritual Courts, and that it ſeems from Cuſtome ſetled in practice of the former times that were then newly paſt. And perhaps it might be in the more ancient times <hi>fori mixti,</hi> and as well exerciſed in the one, as in the other Court; as we have elſewhere ſhewed of the more ancient Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction of Tithes; or it may be, that thoſe <hi>Writs</hi> in the former Chapter, and the like, were but in caſe of Tenants being Teſtators, upon whoſe deaths all their goods were to be ſeiſed by the Sheriff, or other ſuch Officer, and the debt (if any were) paid to the King, <hi>Et reſiduum relinquebatur Executoribus teſtamenti defuncti,</hi> as the words are, both of the Charters of King <hi>John</hi> and <hi>H.</hi> 3. <note n="(a)" place="margin">Cap. 15. magn. Char. quam etiam do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>navit Johannes Rex, uti videre eſt apud Matth. Paris.</note> and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps by that Chapter of the Charter thoſe <hi>Writs</hi> may be interpreted, and <hi>faciatis teneri teſtamentum</hi> may be but only an <hi>amoving</hi> of the Kings hands from the goods, that ſo the Executor might perform the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament; for that the Spiritual Court did from the beginning of <hi>H.</hi> 3. exerciſe a Juriſdiction for recovery of Legacies, is infallibly proved by
<note n="(b)" place="margin">2 H. 3. tit. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hib. 13. 4 H. 3. ibidem. 28. 6 H. 3. ibid. 17. 8 H. 3. ibid. 19.</note> Caſes of 2, 4, 6, <hi>&amp;</hi> 8 <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. and the Attachments upon Prohibitions extant in Records of that time, are, <hi>quare ſecutus eſt placitum in Curia
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Mich. 16 &amp; 17 H. 3. Rot. 15 &amp;c. &amp; 18 H. 3. coram W. de Raleigh, &amp;c. Rot. 36. in arce Londi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſi.</note> Chriſtianitatis de Catallis quae non ſunt de Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtamento vel matrimonio:</hi> and many ſuch more are both in the <hi>Rolls</hi> and in <hi>Matth. Paris.</hi> It appears alſo in 2 <hi>H.</hi> 3. in the Caſe of <hi>Symon Fitz Simon,</hi> that even that Suit for deviſeable Land being deviſed, was thought to be good in the Spiritual Court <hi>ex Cauſa teſtamentaria,</hi> as if <hi>Laicum feodum verſum eſſet in Catallum,</hi> until the deviſee had recovered it: and after the recovery, <hi>iterum incipiebat eſſe Laicum feodum</hi>—as <note n="(d)" place="margin">Lib. 5. Tract. de exceptiontbus, cap. 12 pag. 4091. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Bracton</hi> ſayes, where his Printed Copy is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly corrupted. But it was clear Law in the time of this <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cton,</hi> who was a Judge in the <hi>Common Pleas</hi> in the latter part of <hi>H.</hi> 3. that <hi>locum
<note n="(e)" place="margin">Idem ſo. 4076.</note> non habet probatio in Cauſa teſtamentaria ſi Catalla legen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur &amp; inde agatur in foro Eccleſiaſtico:</hi> and he reckons that of Teſtaments <hi>inter ſpiritualia, &amp; ſpiritualibus annexa,</hi> which agrees exactly in the known and practiſed Conſultations in the <note n="(f)" place="margin">Regiſter. Orig. ſo. 48. (b) &amp;c.</note> Regiſter, <hi>placita de Catallis &amp; debitis, quae ſunt de Teſtamento &amp; Matrimonio, ad forum Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae ſpecialiter dignoſcimus pertinere, &amp;c.</hi> And although in caſe of Legacy, as in caſe of Tithes, the Juriſdiction that gave the recovery of them, was ſometimes in the one, ſometimes in the other Court, before it was reſtrained to the Spiritual only, yet it ſeems by thoſe Caſes of <hi>Henry</hi> the Third's time, which are Teſtimonies beyond exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions, that the Spiritual Juriſdiction over Legacies, was long before in practice; otherwiſe I gueſs that exception <hi>de Teſtamento, &amp; de Matrimonio,</hi> had not been ſo familiar in the Prohibitions of that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:108531:9"/>Age. And notwithſtanding thoſe Caſes out of the Records of King <hi>John</hi>'s and <hi>Henry</hi> the Third his time, the Temporal Court not only prohibited not the Spiritual Court, eſpecially in <hi>Henry</hi> the Third's time, but alſo had not any Conuſance of Suits for perſonal Legacies; for neither have I ever met with any Suit in that kind in the Plea Rolls of <hi>H.</hi> 3. or King <hi>John,</hi> or <hi>Richard</hi> 1. (but very few are extant of the time of the two laſt) neither doth <hi>Bracton</hi> admit any ſuch thing. And the Author of <hi>Fleta</hi> in the time of <hi>E.</hi> 1. tells us ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly,
<note n="(g)" place="margin">Fleta lib. 2. cap. 57. Sect. Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor.</note> 
                  <hi>de Cauſa Teſtamentaria ſicut nec de cauſa Matrimoniali Curia Regis ſe non intromittet.</hi> But the beginning of that practice of the <hi>Extrinſecal</hi> Juriſdiction in the Spiritual Court, is even as difficult to find, as that other of <hi>Probates. Linwood</hi> tells us, that
<note n="(h)" place="margin">Ad tit. de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtam. c. Statut. verb. Eccleſiaſt. libertat.</note> 
                  <hi>libertas quoad ſecundum ſcilicet, puniendum impedientes quo minus teſtamenta &amp; altimae voluntates defunctorum procedant, ortum habet à privilegits etiam in ea parte conceſſis, &amp; à conſuetudine ſimiliter de ſcientia Regum Angl. diutius obſervata:</hi> and further, <hi>potuit</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>habere ortum</hi> out of thoſe
<note n="(i)" place="margin">De Epiſc. &amp; Cler. &amp; nulli 28. &amp; ſiquis ad deſignan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, 49, &amp;c.</note> Laws in the Code that made the Biſhop a Protector of Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacies <hi>in pios uſus.</hi> It might be alſo in regard of the purpoſe of thoſe Laws in themſelves; and it were no great wonder, that the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Court might have gained Juriſdiction over all perſonal Lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies under colour of ſuch as were given <hi>in pios uſus:</hi> But perhaps it will not be admitted for probability enough, that any part of the Code being of the Imperial or Civil Law, was ever ſo received here in <hi>England,</hi> as that it could induce any alteration touching the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction of the Crown, that is, touching this <hi>Extrinſecal</hi> Juriſdiction which (as is ſhewed) did belong to the Temporal Courts: but who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever will not admit of any ſuch conjecture, muſt yet remember, that preſently from King <hi>Stephen</hi>'s time, when the <hi>Civil Law</hi> was new born into the light, it having lain forgotten by the ſpace of Six Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years before in the <hi>Weſtern Empire,</hi> the Code and other parts of that Law were familiarly read by our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Lawyers; and I think as well by our Common as Canon Lawyers: to omit that Caſe of <hi>Mabile of Franchiville,</hi> wherein, it ſeems, a ſpecial regard was had to the Civil
<note n="(k)" place="margin">Cod. de lib. Natur. l. 2. Matr. &amp; Author. 89, &amp;c.</note> Law, that permits not a meer Baſtard and Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion <hi>ex Teſtamento</hi> againſt a lawful Heir of Blood; for otherwiſe how could <hi>Richard</hi> the Uncle's Inſtitution, as it ſeems by a former Will have made colour of right for him, againſt the latter Will which <hi>Mabile</hi> pretended, unleſs he relyed upon her being a Baſtard. But I ſhould think it probable enough, that the Original of this Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for Legacies, was out of the <hi>Canon Law.</hi> And that eſpecially from that Canon <hi>Si haeredes, &amp;c.</hi> before cited; for although the <hi>Decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals,</hi> wherein it ſtands now authorized for a general Law, were firſt publiſhed but in 24 <hi>H.</hi> 3. by <hi>Gregory</hi> the Ninth, and that we ſee by infallible teſtimony already brought, that Legacies before that time, were recoverable in the Spiritual Court, yet by likelihood that very Canon was inſerted in all or ſome of thoſe eight more ancient Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilations of the Canons authorized by ſome former Popes; (which is the more probable, becauſe we find it alſo in <hi>Burchard</hi>) and ſo it might be, long before ſufficient ground of this <hi>Extrinſecal</hi> Juriſdiction in the Ordinary; but I ſought here for Authority more than I durſt be bold in conjectures, which I leave to every mans judgement.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:108531:10"/>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:108531:10"/>
            <head>PART II. OF THE Diſpoſition or Adminiſtration OF <hi>Inteſtates Goods.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>In whom it was in the time of the</hi> Saxons.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the <hi>Saxons</hi> time it was in the Lord of him that dyed (underſtand the Chief Lord) in caſe the Inteſtate were a Tenant, and dyed at home in peace: But in caſe he were no Tenant, or dyed in his Lords Army, then it was (it ſeems) as other Inheritance under the Juriſdiction of that Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Court within whoſe Territory the goods were: This may be proved out of the Laws of that time, which ordain, that upon the death of an Inteſtate, whom they call cƿiale aƿe, the Lord <note n="(a)" place="margin">Canuti. leg. cap. 68.</note> is only to have the <hi>Heriotts</hi> due to him, which are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo appointed by <note n="(b)" place="margin">Ejuſdem leg. cap. 68.</note> the Laws of the ſame time, <hi>That by his</hi> (the Lords) <hi>advice or judgement his</hi> (the Inteſtates) <hi>goods be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided among his Wife and Children and the next of Kin, according as to every one of them of right belongs,</hi> that is, according to the nearneſs of Kindred, if no Children or Nephews from them be; for it muſt, I ſuppoſe, be underſtood, that the ſucceſſion was ſuch, that the Children excluded all their Kindred, and of their Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:108531:11"/>the next ſucceeded, according to that in <hi>Tacitus</hi>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">De moribus Germanorum.</note> of his <hi>Germans,</hi> whoſe Cuſtoms were doubtleſs mixt with our <hi>Engliſh Saxons, haeredes,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>ſucceſſoreſque ſint cuique liberi, &amp; nullum Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtamentum.</hi> But it ſeems, Chriſtianity afterward brought in the free power of making Teſtaments amongſt them, <hi>Si liberi non ſunt, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ximus gradus in poſſeſſione fratres, patrui, Avunculi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But this is expreſt only in caſe the Tenant dyed at home and in peace; for if he dyed in his
<note n="(d)" place="margin">Canut. legibus, cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>5.</note> Lords Army, both the Heriort was forgiven, and the Inheritance both of Goods and Lands was to be divided <hi>as it ought,</hi> which was, it ſeems, by the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction of the <hi>Temporal Court</hi> within whoſe Territory the Death or Goods were; for in that caſe, it is not ſaid, that the Lords Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was to be uſed, but that the Heirs ſhould divide all; or, as the words in the <hi>Confeſſor</hi>'s Law are, <hi>habeant
<note n="(e)" place="margin">Leg. Ed. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fell. cap. de hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiis.</note> haeredes ejus pecuniam &amp; terram ejus ſine aliqua diminutione, &amp; recte dividant interſe;</hi> where the right of the Heir both to Lands and Goods is expreſly deſigned, but the Judge that ſhould give it them, not mentioned. Therefore it ſeems, it remained as other parts of the Common Law, under the Temporal Juriſdiction, as by the <note n="(f)" place="margin">F. S. Inſtit. de bonorum poſſeſſione.</note> Civil Law it is under the Pretors.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:108531:11"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>In whom after the</hi> Normans <hi>until King</hi> John<hi>'s time.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>UNtil King <hi>John</hi>'s time it ſeems the Juriſdiction over <hi>Inteſtates</hi> Goods, was as of other Inheritance alſo, in the Temporal Courts: yet no ſufficient Teſtimony is found to prove it expreſly; only when the Common Laws of thoſe times ſpeak of <hi>Inteſtates,</hi> they determine the ſucceſſion by like diviſion as thoſe of the <hi>Saxon</hi> times. <note n="(a)" place="margin">Adjiciuntur In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulphe Crolandenſi MS. in Bibliotheca Cottoniana.</note> In Laws attributed to <hi>William</hi> the Firſt we read, <hi>Si home moruſt ſans deviſe, ſi departent les Infants l'erite inter ſei per ovell.</hi> And after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in <hi>H.</hi> 1. <note n="(b)" place="margin">Apud Matth. Paris.</note> Laws, <hi>ſi quis Baronum vel hominum meorum pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventus vel Armis vel infirmitate pecuniam ſuam nec dederit, nec dare diſpoſuerit, uxor ſua, ſive liberi, aut Parentes, &amp; legitimi homines ſui pro anima ejus eam dividant, ſicut eis melius viſum fuerit.</hi> Here is the <hi>firſt mention,</hi> as I remember, of any thing occurring in our Laws or Hiſtories, of the diſpoſition of the Inteſtates Goods, <hi>pro anima ejus,</hi> which indeed might have been fitly ſubjected to the view at leaſt of the Church. But no mention as yet being of any Eccleſiaſtical Power that tends that way, I rather think that heretofore no uſe or practice was of Adminiſtration committed, direction given, or med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with the Goods by the Ordinaries; but all was by the <hi>Friends</hi> or Kindred <hi>juxta Conſilium diſcretorum virorum,</hi> as the words are in <note n="(c)" place="margin">Will. Novoburg. hiſt. l. 3. c. 22.</note> the Statutes made for ſuch as ſhould dye in the <hi>Holy War</hi> with <hi>Richard</hi> the Firſt.</p>
               <p>Neither doth that of <hi>Glanvill,</hi> which was written under <hi>H.</hi> 2. tell us of any thing of the Ordinaries Power in this caſe, although it hath expreſs mention of <hi>Teſtaments,</hi> and the Churches Juriſdiction of them. Indeed we there find, that if no Executor be named, then <note n="(d)" place="margin">Glanvill. lib. 7. cap 6.</note> 
                  <hi>poſſunt propinqui &amp; conſanguinei Teſtatoris,</hi> take upon them the Executorſhip, and ſue in the Kings Court againſt ſuch as hinder the due payment of Legacies; which alſo agrees well enough with that before cited out of the Laws of <hi>H.</hi> 1. Neither is there in <hi>Gualter Mapes</hi> his <hi>Apocalypſis</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a bitter Satyr againſt the Abuſes of the Spiritual Courts in <hi>Henry</hi> the Seconds time) nor in <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Salisbury</hi>'s Epiſtles, that have many particulars of the exerciſed Juriſdiction of the Church, any thing oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring, that touches upon any Eccleſiaſtical Powers of this nature.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:108531:12"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>In whom after the time of King</hi> John.</head>
               <p>BUt in that Charter of Liberties both for the Church and Laity made to the Baronage of <hi>England</hi> in the ſeventeenth of King <hi>John</hi> 
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">Reperiuntur ſeorſimſaepius exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaria illius diplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matis &amp; penes Math. Paris, Rogerum Wendover MS. &amp; Thom. Rudburne MS. entant, ſed in Archivis non extant.</note> in <hi>Reningmead</hi> an expreſs Ordinance is, <hi>That if any Free-man dyed inteſtate, his Chattels were to be diſpoſed of by the hands of his next of kin, by the view of the Church,</hi> that is, direction and advice being thereto given by the Ordinary, as I underſtand, <hi>ſaving to all Creditors their debts:</hi> the words of it were, <hi>Si aliquis liber homo inteſtatus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſerit, Catalla ſua per manus propinquorum, parentum, &amp; amicorum ſuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, per viſum Eccleſiae diſtribuantur, ſalvis unicuique debitis, quae defun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus eis debebat.</hi> That Charter of King <hi>John</hi> is almoſt the ſame ſylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles with the common one that we now uſe by the name of the <hi>Grand Charter</hi> of 9 <hi>H.</hi> 3. exemplified by the Kings Patent of 28 <hi>E.</hi> 1. But this of Inteſtates, and two or three other Chapters for the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects Liberty, are more in that of King <hi>John</hi>'s, than is found in the Exemplification of 28 <hi>E.</hi> 1. However <hi>Matthew Paris</hi> and <hi>Roger</hi> of <hi>Wendover</hi> when they ſpeak of <hi>H.</hi> 3. granting it, ſo refer their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to this of King <hi>John,</hi> that they tell us, that that of <hi>H.</hi> 3. was the ſelf ſame in every particular; and therefore omit the repetition of it. And indeed, although in the common Printed <hi>Magna Charta</hi> of <hi>H.</hi> 3.
<note place="margin">V. Manuſcriptum noſtr. de Magn. Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, cap. 16. in fine.</note> and in the Roll alſo of 28 <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. in the <hi>Tower,</hi> where the Exemplification is, this Ordinance touching <hi>Inteſtates</hi> be wanting, yet in very many of the ancienteſt Manuſcripts of the old Statutes, that of <hi>H.</hi> 3. hath the ſame words as we have here tranſcribed it from King <hi>John</hi>'s, and that in the ſame place of his Charter as that in King <hi>John</hi>'s; that is, between the eighteenth Chapter; <hi>Si quis tenens, &amp;c.</hi> and the nineteenth, <hi>Nullus Conſtabularius, &amp;c.</hi> And it is to be underſtood, that the greateſt Prelates of the Clergy of that time, as <hi>Canterbury, London, Wincheſter, Pandulphus</hi> the Popes <hi>Nuncio,</hi> the Maſter of the <hi>Temple,</hi> and divers other Biſhops were on the Kings part, when that of King <hi>John</hi> was granted. And it is probable enough, that when they ſaw that a Charter of Liberties muſt of neceſſity be granted to the <hi>Baronage,</hi> they ſo wrought alſo, that they might inſert this one for the advantage of their Epiſcopal Government. And they had good colour to think and perſwade, that ſome ſuch thing was fit for them, in regard it was now clearly taken, that ſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution was to be made <hi>pro anima inteſtati,</hi> the <hi>care</hi> of <hi>ſouls</hi> being the chiefeſt part of their common pretences for increaſe of their power and greatneſs. And hence I ſuppoſe, it ſoon came to paſs, that the next of kin had the power of diſpoſition committed by the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaries, and that in Letters or otherwiſe by vertue of that <hi>per viſum Eccleſiae,</hi> which was, I think, the textual ground of right of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of Adminiſtration by the Clergy: This of King <hi>John</hi>'s being iterated in <hi>Henry</hi> the Thirds Charter (however omitted in the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplification) was it ſeems that proviſion ſpoken of in Cardinal <hi>Othobon's Legatins, Proinde ſuper bonis ab inteſtato decedentium,</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">Cap. cum mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis incerta.</note> ſo
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:108531:12"/>are the words, <hi>proviſionem quae olim à Praelatis Regni Angliae cum ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probatione Regis &amp; Baronum dicitur emanaſſe, firmiter approbantes, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrictius inhibemus ne Prelati vel alii quicunque bona inteſtatorum quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque modo recipiant, vel occupent contra proviſionem praemiſſam.</hi> What <hi>proviſion</hi> is it more likely that this was, than that of the Grand Charter both of King <hi>John</hi> and <hi>H.</hi> 3. and the words <hi>à Praelatis dicitur emanaſſe,</hi> juſtifies what we have conjectured of the purpoſe of the Prelates, when they ſaw they could not but yield with the King, to an eſtabliſhment of Laws, by that Charter, made indeed in a Parliament of that age. The ſame I ſuppoſe that which is meant in the <note n="(c)" place="margin">Provinc. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitut. tit. de immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitate Eccleſiae, C. accidit novitate.</note> Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Arch-biſhop <hi>Stafford,</hi> where it is taken for granted, that the Churches power of diſpoſition of Inteſtates goods <hi>pro ſalute anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp; in pios uſus,</hi> was a thing <hi>conſenſu Regio &amp; megnatum Regni Angl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanquam pro jure Ecoleſiaſticá<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> libertate ab olim ordinatum, &amp;c.</hi> Where <hi>Linwood</hi> modeſtly confeſſes, that he could not find in what Kings time this Ordinance was made. But <hi>Johannes de Athona,</hi> upon that of <hi>Otho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon,</hi> though he rightly call that proviſion, <hi>Proviſio Parliamentalis:</hi> yet moſt ignorantly and ridiculouſly <note n="(d)" place="margin">Jo. de Athona ad Legat. Othobonum c. cum mortis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certa.</note> tells us, <hi>that the proviſion there underſtood, is the Statute of Weſtminſter,</hi> 2. <hi>Cap.</hi> 21. <hi>cum poſt mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem,</hi> which he makes alſo to have I know not what reference to the Statute of <hi>Gloceſter.</hi> But this ſlipt from him either in a dream, or through the utmoſt neglect of thoſe infallible characters of truth, that the denoting of times affords us, for that <hi>Legatin</hi> of <hi>Othobon</hi> was made in <hi>London</hi> in <note n="(e)" place="margin">Praeter Annales obvios, Linwood ad C. quia verb. Ottobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, tit. de conſtitutio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus.</note> 53 <hi>H.</hi> 3. and at ſuch time as that <hi>Proviſion</hi> was yet extant in the <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> uſed by our Lawyers. But the Statutes of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the ſecond, and of <hi>Gloceſter</hi> were under <hi>E.</hi> 1. the one in the ſixth, the other in the thirteenth of him; how then could <hi>Othobon</hi> think of it in his Legatin, or could <hi>John de Athona</hi> have thought ſo, if he had allowed the Title of his Gloſs, which ſuppoſes in the point, that the Conſtitutions of <hi>Othobon</hi> were publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the year 1248. which had it been in 1268. had agreed with truth; but doubtleſs the Numeral Letters of MCCLXVIII were tranſpoſed into MCCXLVIII. and thence only that Error.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:108531:13"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>How that ſo granted by King</hi> John<hi>'s Charter in Parliament hath continued in practice.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AFter that Law of the ſeventeenth of K. <hi>John,</hi> it ſeems the <hi>next of kin</hi> diſpoſed of Inteſtates Goods by the teſtimony and direction of the Church; for ſo <hi>per viſum</hi> denotes, as we ſee in <hi>per viſum pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borum &amp; legalium hominum</hi> in Writs of Summons and the like: but I have not ſeen any practice of it teſtified in King <hi>John</hi>'s time. And under <hi>H.</hi> 3. however it were omitted in his Charter at the Exemplifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, the ſame <hi>viſus Eccleſiae</hi> continued; ſo ſayes <hi>Bracton</hi> that then lived, and was a Judge of that time, <hi>Si <note n="(a)" place="margin">Bracton. lib. 2. de acq. rer. dom. cap. 26. ſect. 2.</note> liber homo inteſtatus &amp; ſubito deceſſerit, dominus ſuus nil intromittat de bonis defuncti, niſi de hoc tantum, quod ad ipſum pertineret, (ſc. quod habeat ſuum Heriott.) ſed ad Eccleſiam &amp; amicos pertinebit executio bonorum.</hi> Yet it ſeems al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, that notwithſtanding the right of the Church thus ordained, and the ſucceſſion of next of kin ſo included in the Ordinance, both the Lords in ſome places, according to their former right, ſtill uſurp ſome power over the diſpoſition of Inteſtates Goods, againſt the will of the Ordinaries: and on the other ſide alſo, the Ordinaries, inſtead of giving direction for a true diſpoſition of ſuch Goods, get poſſeſſion of them, and commit them often, or at leaſt too great a part of them, to the uſe either of themſelves, or of the Church, and ſo <hi>defrauded</hi> thoſe to whom by the right of natural ſucceſſion they pertained. For that of the Lords, <hi>Bracton</hi> his noting it as a thing denyed them, compared with what we find among Articles granted in the Synod of <hi>London</hi> held under <hi>Boniface</hi> Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> in 42 <hi>H.</hi> 3. proves it, <hi>Idem quod mortuo</hi> (ſo is the <note n="(b)" place="margin">In Annal. Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonenſis coenobii penes v. cl. Thom. Allen Oxonienſem MS. A. 1257.</note> Article) <hi>laico ſine Teſtamento non capiantur bona ipſius in manus dominorum. Sed inde ſolvantur de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bita ipſius, &amp; reſidua in uſus filiorum ſuorum, &amp; proximorum indigenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um pro ſalute animae defuncti in pios uſus per Ordinarios committantur, niſi quatenus fuerit domino ſuo obligatus.</hi> Here we ſee by the way plainly that the diſtribution <hi>in pios uſus,</hi> was the deviſing them among the next of kin, according to their nearneſs and want; not an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying them to other uſes, at the Ordinaries arbitrary diſpoſition. But alſo that the Ordinary did in this Age ſometimes uſurp the Goods of Inteſtates againſt the next of kin, is enough proved out of that Legatine Conſtitution of <hi>Othobon, cum mortis incerta, &amp;c.</hi> where it was ordained as you ſee before; ſo in the words of it, that they ſhould not diſpoſe of them otherwiſe than according as that Grant was in the <hi>Grand Charter;</hi> that is, to the benefit of the next of blood: But the Ordinaries had about this time, againſt the intent of that <hi>Charter,</hi> ſo abuſed the right of ſucceſſion, that it was related
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Innocent. 4. tit. de Simionia, c. ad Apoſtolicum.</note> for a conſtant truth, that the <hi>Cuſtome in Britania</hi> was, that <hi>tertia pars bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum decedentium ab inteſtato in opus Eccleſiae &amp; pauperum diſpenſanda, &amp;c.</hi> as <hi>Innocent</hi> the Fourth his words are, who lived and wrote in the time of <hi>H.</hi> 3. What other ground than the Ordinaries <hi>ill dealing</hi> with the next of blood was for that <hi>tertia pars</hi> I conceive not; unleſs the Pope
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:108531:13"/>had ſome ſuch other Teſtimony touching it, as we find in an old Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript Volume titled <note n="(d)" place="margin">MS in Theſau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro Cottoniano c. 31. de diviſione haredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis.</note> 
                  <hi>Statuta Synodorum</hi> written in an hand of near ſeven hundred years ſince, being a Collection out of the Fathers and old Councils, made as it ſeems by ſome <hi>Britain</hi> or <hi>Iriſh-man,</hi> as we have elſewhere conjectured. In that <hi>Statuta Synodorum</hi> occurrs <hi>Orig. in lib. de haeredibus: pater moriens det tertiam partem filiis, &amp; tertiam Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſari, &amp; tertiam Eccleſiae; ſi non habuerit Eccleſiam, det pauperibus, &amp; ſi non habuerit Caeſarem nec Eccleſiam, dividat inter filios &amp; pauperes.</hi> But what Author this is cited out of, I am equally ignorant, as I know not at all who was the Author of the whole Collection, or whence he had many other of his Authorities. And other things that Volume hath out of ſome old Synod of <hi>Ireland,</hi> which makes to our preſent purpoſe, if the Canons of that Synod had been at all binding in this State. And it was no ſuch wonder, that ſome ſuch practice might be under <hi>H.</hi> 3. for ſince alſo in the time of <hi>E.</hi> 3. the Church <hi>ſo uſurped</hi> in their Juriſdiction of <hi>Probates,</hi> that they made the Executors wait on their Officials at uncertain and remote places, and then alſo put them, at times, to the Ranſom of the fourth or fifth part of the Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors Goods, before they would give them <hi>Probate;</hi> which was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained
<note n="(e)" place="margin">Parl. 21 E. 3. Cro. Hill. art. 51. &amp; conſule ſi vis Parl. octab. Puriſ. 23 E. 3. art. 35. <hi>in Archivis.</hi>
                  </note> of in Parliament amongſt the Grievances of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:108531:14"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Of that of</hi> bona Inteſtatorum in manus Domini Regis capi ſolebant.</head>
               <p>FOr that of <hi>bona Inteſtatorum in manus Domini Regis capi ſolebant,</hi> for which is cited <note n="(a)" place="margin">Henſloes Caſe apud v. cl. Ed. Coke part 9. ſect. 39, 40.</note> the Cloſe Roll of 7 <hi>H.</hi> 3. <hi>Rot.</hi> 16. it is alſo moſt true, if rightly apprehended. All that appears in the Record is, that the King wrote to the Sheriff of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> that <hi>conſtat nobis per in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitionem nobis miſſam ſub ſigillo Stephani de Segrave, &amp; aliorum probo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp; legalium hominum, quod Richardus filius Dunae non obiit inteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> and therefore he commands, that the Sheriff ſhould deliver all the Goods of the ſaid <hi>Fitz-dune in manus noſtras capta,</hi> to the Prior of <hi>Loketon,</hi> and others his Executors, <hi>ad faciendum Teſtamentum:</hi> neither are there any words that tell us of any <hi>capiſolebant,</hi> or that theſe were taken in regard of dying inteſtate only. Indeed it appears not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently in the Writ, why they were taken; but it is moſt probable, that the <hi>ſeiſure</hi> was for ſome debt due to the Crown from the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, which afterward not appearing, or being ſatisfied, or it appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Executors by the taking upon them the execution of the Teſtament, would ſubject themſelves to the payment of it, it was fit enough to a move the Kings hands, and deliver all over to the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors: He that well conſiders the Statute of <hi>Magna Charta cap.</hi> 18. <hi>Si quis tenens,</hi> and compares it with that of <hi>Bracton,</hi> where he tells us, that the Law was clear, that <hi>if any man dyed indebted to the King, the Sheriff might <note n="(b)" place="margin">Bracton. lib. 2. de acq. rerum dom. cap. 26. ſect. 2.</note> imbreviare, &amp; attachiare cattalla defuncti,</hi> will ſoon ſee the probability of this, howſoever the words of the Statute are only of the Kings Tenants: And it concludes alſo, as if it were only in caſe of the death of a Teſtator in regard of <hi>relinquatur executoribus ad fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciendum teſtamentum defuncti;</hi> but plainly, that <hi>ad faciendum, &amp;c.</hi> hath equal reference to the Inteſtates as to Teſtators: for no name of an <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrator</hi> being then uſually known, all were called <hi>Executors</hi> that medled with the <hi>Inteſtates</hi> Goods; and thoſe Executors were <hi>executores qui faciebant Teſtamentum,</hi> that is, which inſtead of the Inteſtate
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Ita facere te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtamentum nomine defuncti ſumitur a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Canonici juris peritos. videſis Zebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam prax. Epiſcop. verb. legatum, ſect. 8.</note> did take ſuch order after his death with his Goods, as they thought he would have done if he had made a Teſtament; which may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived alſo out of the uſe remembred in that time, wherein ſick men being unable, neither having time to expreſs their meaning, choſe out ſome friends that might be <hi>ſuper <note n="(d)" place="margin">Mos iſte repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritur apud Matth. Paris, hiſtor. major, pag. 982. Ubi de Pontificia conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one de inteſtatis edit. Londinenſ.</note> hoc expreſſores &amp; exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutores;</hi> which friends appointing of Legacies (as if the Inteſtate had given them) and making diſpoſition of Inteſtates Goods, were as Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaments of thoſe Inteſtates; and they did truly as Executors <hi>facere Teſtamentum defuncti,</hi> in which ſenſe it might be ſpoken of any Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors or Adminiſtrators that intermedled in thoſe times. And many Writs occurr in the Cloſe Roll of King <hi>John</hi> and <hi>H.</hi> 3. that have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly in them the <hi>amoving</hi> of the Kings hands from the Goods of the dead, when the ſeiſure had been only for the debts to the Crown, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Statute of <hi>Magna Charta</hi> (which in ſubſtance is the Law at this day) and <hi>Bracton,</hi> by reaſon whereof, I ſee not cauſe enough,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:108531:14"/>why we ſhould underſtand that of 7 <hi>H.</hi> 3. to prove any ſuch thing, as a Cuſtom of the Kings diſpoſing or ſeiſing of the Inteſtates Goods, eſpecially in regard that in the paſſages of the Law, Lawyers and Records of that time, no mention is of any thing that affirms it to be a Cuſtom, or touches it as a common uſe.</p>
               <p>But admit that in <hi>Fitz-dunes</hi> Caſe it had been ſo, that the taking of the Goods into the Kings hand, had been becauſe of his dying <hi>Inteſtate</hi> only. It may therefore be accounted rather as a particular of the irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular practice of that time, than any example to prove a Cuſtom; and whoſoever is but acquainted with the courſe of the Records of King <hi>John</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> the Third his time, muſt ſoon ſee Writs enough that agree not ſo much as with any ſetled courſe of Law, but taſte ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of ſome ſudden or arbitrary courſe of granting them. Indeed ſome two years before that of <hi>Fitz-dune,</hi> there is an example in <hi>Bedford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> that might ſeem more fully to prove what is collected out of the other: the Writ is thus, <hi>Rex <note n="(e)" place="margin">Clauſ. 5 H. 3. par. 2. memb. 3.</note> Vicecom. Bedford ſalutem. Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipimus tibi quod blada &amp; catalla quae fuerunt Roberti de Inſula &amp; Roſſiae uxoris ejus defunct. in Wahall &amp; Brokeberge areſtari facias &amp; ſalvo cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtodiri, donec diſcuſſum fuerit in curia noſtra ad quem catalla illa pertinent, &amp; aliud inde praecipimus;</hi> but this is often enough ſeconded with other examples that have for the moſt part a mention of the Defuncts debts to the Crown, that it cannot otherwiſe be underſtood, but either as founded upon that Law of ſeiſing upon the Goods for debt to the Crown by Prerogative, or as an example (amongſt many of other kinds) that diſcovers a more arbitrary courſe ſometimes in proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, than later time hath permitted. And according to one of thoſe wayes (but the firſt that is upon the Statute of the <hi>Grand Charter</hi> is the fitteſt and moſt probable) muſt that alſo be interpreted, where <note n="(f)" place="margin">Clauſ. 17 H. 3. memb. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>H.</hi> 3. ſends a Writ to the Sheriff of <hi>Rutland</hi> to <hi>command him, that notwithſtanding that</hi> Robert de Weſton <hi>a Pariſhioner of</hi> Weſton <hi>were drowned, and dyed inteſtate,</hi> he ſhould yet <hi>facere Willielmo de S. Lando</hi> (that is, to the Parſon of the Pariſh) <hi>habere nomine Eccleſiae ſuae id quod ad eum pertinet, habendum de catallis quae fuerunt praedicti Roberti, ſecundum conſuetudines partium illarum:</hi> that was for the <hi>mortuarie,</hi> which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly and under that name then was determinable in the Spiritual Court.</p>
               <p>But ſurely we muſt conclude, that if there were any ſuch practice by the Officers of the Crown in the time of <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. to ſeiſe <hi>Inteſtates</hi> goods generally, it was not ſo much the Law of the time; for if ſo, the Records could not be but as full of examples of it, as the time was of the death of Inteſtates, which queſtionleſs were very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; but ſome ſuch temporary uſurpation, as in 31 <hi>H.</hi> 3. Pope <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> the Fourth here had for a while executed by his Miniſters the <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſcans</hi> and <hi>Dominicans,</hi> in not only getting into his own hands, but alſo to his own uſe,
<note n="(g)" place="margin">Matth. Paris, ſo. 959. Edit. Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinenſ.</note> all the <hi>Goods of the Clergy-men</hi> that dyed <hi>Inteſtate</hi> through <hi>England,</hi> which as <hi>Matthew Paris</hi> that then lived, relates it, <hi>cum audiſſet dominus Rex, deteſtans Romanae Curiae augmentoſam &amp; mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplicem avaritiam, hoc fieri prohibuit, comperiens illud ad damnum Regni &amp; ſuum redundare praejudicium.</hi> Afterward in the time of <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. it appears by the Statute of <hi>Weſtm.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 21. <hi>cum poſt mortem, &amp;c.</hi> that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:108531:15"/>the Goods of <hi>Inteſtates</hi> did come <hi>ad Ordinarios diſponenda,</hi> which agrees with that of <hi>Bracton</hi> before cited, and iterated in the ſame ſyllables in <hi>Fleta</hi> 
                  <note n="(h)" place="margin">Fleta l. 2. c. 57.</note> which was written under <hi>E.</hi> 1. And the diſpoſition of <hi>Lateſtates</hi> Goods was enquired after in thoſe dayes <note n="(i)" place="margin">Quod videre eſt in Cro. Wigorn. Eccleſiae in Biblioth. Cott. ſub initio E. 1.</note> amongſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction. And afterwards by the Statute of 31 <hi>E.</hi> 3. the Ordinary was compelled to commit the adminiſtration of Inteſtates Goods to the next of kin: after which Statute the name of <hi>Adminiſtrator</hi> was common as their Office; and by that name ſuch to whom the Ordinary committed were ſued, although before that time they were ſuable by the name of <hi>Executors,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">28 E. 3 fo. 21. <hi>a.</hi>
                  </note> and perhaps alſo by the name of <hi>Adminiſtrators:</hi> 
                  <note n="(k)" place="margin">Videſis 25 E. 3. fo. 54. <hi>a.</hi> ſed &amp; plura in l. 9. Vir. cl. E. Cook par. 5. fo. 82. &amp; par. 9. f. 39. &amp; 40. &amp; 19 Ed. 3. tit. Cove nant. 24.</note> but that name is ſcarce found (as I think not at all) given a Defendant to an Action brought before ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven years after the Statute of 31 <hi>E.</hi> 3. And in the Parliament Rolls of 17 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. the <hi>Adminiſtrators</hi> are deſigned only by the <hi>Ceux que ſont per l'Eveſque ordines en lieu des Executors,</hi> where a Petition is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered <note n="(l)" place="margin">Quindena Paſch. 17 E. 3. Artic. 49.</note> by the Commons, that ſuch might have the like Actions as their <hi>Inteſtates:</hi> but the King anſwers, <hi>Quant à ceux qui devient inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate le Roy voet que l'Eveſque eit action en tien caſe depuis que il doit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponder as autres.</hi> But from that of 31 <hi>E.</hi> 3. ſaving only the alteration by 21 <hi>H.</hi> 8. the Law hath continued uniformly to this day.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:108531:15"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
